In the tshuva of Rav Moshe in
source number 11, okay? In source number
11. So we're going to go through
a number of examples because we talked
about the comment of the Rema. Right?
So the Rema says that l'chatchila, l'chatchila
one is not able to add dairy
to parve food כדין בן יומו פליישיק
pot. Let's repeat that again. The Rema
says l'chatchila I cannot take a ben
yomo pot, cook pasta in that pot,
and then know that I am adding
milchik to those noodles. Okay? The Rema
says you cannot do that. Bedieved, if
it happened, we'd be okay. So if
you look in Rav Moshe, so Rav
Moshe's going to deal with the following
shaila: could I on an erev Shabbos,
let's say, could I cook or do
something with fish in a dairy ben
yomo pot, because I know that that's
all the pots that I have right
now, everything else is in the sink.
So says Rav Moshe, it's a machlokes,
mashma mehatz, he quotes the Taz and
the Shach, דוקא כדי אוכלן בכותח אסר
לכתחילה. Says no, what did the Rema
say is assur? The Rema said it's
assur to make that pasta knowing full
well that what am I going to
do with it? I'm going to eat
with cheese. אבל כדי להעלות אחר כך
על כלי חלב מותר לכתחילה. But simply
to just say that I'm going to,
I know that I'm going to put
it on a flayshik plate, that's a
different story. So I have a dairy
ben yomo pot, it's erev Shabbos, and
I need to make fish, okay? So
that's all the pot that I have.
So what do I do? I use
that pot, but I'm not planning on
eating that fish with cheese. So it
might just be that what plate is
it going on? It's going on a
flayshik plate. That, says Rav Moshe, that
seems to be that we're going to
be meikel with that. Rav Moshe is
very meikel about this. About, he quotes
the P'ri Megadim, P'ri Megadim in the
Mishna Brura, סובר דאסור גם לבשל בכלי
חלב להעלות בכלי בשר, that the P'ri
Megadim says that it would be assur,
but l'maiseh Rav Moshe is meikel and
you can deliberately cook or fry fish
in a dairy ben yomo pot to
serve on flayshik dishes. Good? L'chatchila. L'chatchila,
right, l'chatchila because to Michael's point, the
l'chatchila, the plate is cold. Right, the
plate is cold even if it was
hot. I don't know why the plate
would be hot, but what if you
only have one pot? Would that really
be called l'chatchila? Like you need to
make the fish for Shabbos, and that's
your only pot. Is that really called
l'chatchila at that point? Yeah, no, because
we're, yeah, you're focused on the pot,
but the result here is that it's
just the plate. Meaning if I knew
that I wanted to make that eat
that fish with dairy, that would not
be l'chatchila. But if I know that
I'm doing it and the worst thing
that's going to happen is it's going
on a flayshik plate, then we're going
to be okay with it. In this
case, just you're cooking it in a
dairy pot, there's not really an issue
with cheese. No, the question is can
it go on a flayshik plate? Right.
Yeah. So the P'ri Megadim is still
machmir about it. P'ri Megadim's still machmir
about it. Okay. So if you look
in source 12, what happens if the
plate is very hot? So the Aruch
Hashulchan in source number 12 paskens the
following: וזה שכתב דליקח מכלי שלהן מותר
לכתחילה. And we say that you can
put, you can place hot parve food
cooked in a dairy or, other way
around, doesn't make a difference, on a
ben yomo flayshik pot, on a hot
dairy plate, כלומר ליתן דבר שנתבשל בכלי
חלב בכלי בן יומו שנתבשל אף כשהוא
רותח. Says the Aruch Hashulchan, this is
true even if it's hot because there's
so many nesinas tams here that we're
not worried. Because I have one tam
that made the flayshik plate flayshik, and
I have the fish that's only milchik
because of the milchik pot, those two
things are not creating any issur on
my plate right now. So for some
reason you had a really boiling hot
plate, that's what you do, and you
cooked fish in a dairy ben yomo
pot, you could put that fish straight
onto that flayshik plate and you could
just go to town. Say the plate
just came out of the dishwasher, hot.
Doesn't matter. That's hot. That's what we
call hot. Yeah. Okay. Very good. Okay.
I'm going to skip a little bit
of this stuff, also my notes weren't
printed so I don't know what's happening.
All right, there is another piece here
that we will talk about about a
davar charif. Right? Because if for example,
the Rema, I think the Rema, hold
on. Yeah, if you look at the
Rema, just to share this briefly, the
Rema in Tzadi Heh Bais, there's that
big Rema that we mentioned, so the
Rema has a number of halachos. So
the Rema... It says the following, if
you have the red Shulchan Aruch, it's
the last line: v'chozer, this whole idea
of the not barnat כשהמאכל אינו דבר
חריף that the thing that I am
cooking is not a davar charif. If
the food that is being cooked is
a davar charif, then the svara that
I have a fleishik ben yomo, I'm
sorry. The Rama says, parve food cooked
in an eino ben yomo pot l'chat-chila
you can eat it with dairy. Get
eino ben yomo, l'chat-chila you can eat
it with dairy. The Rama says that's
not true if the thing that you
are being cooked is a davar charif.
Okay, onions, garlic, things like that. Okay,
radishes. Ah, hold on, well it depends
on how much they're cooked. Depends. If
they're, if they're like cooked in sauce
that's one thing, but if you, if
you cook parve food in a fleishik
pot, parve food in a fleishik pot,
okay, right? So the meat flavor comes
out of the walls into the parve
food, so we say that's barnat, right?
That's, that's already weakened. But if you
have a davar charif, the davar charif
has an ability to be m'sorer that
taste, to reawaken it, and therefore if
you, again, this is why always be
careful with onions. If you call me
up and that shayla starts with onions,
I'm gonna hang up. Okay? Just telling
you that right now. Okay? So if
you, if you fried onions in an
eino ben yomo fleishik pot. I used
the pot yesterday. In an eino ben
yomo fleishik pot. I used this pot
two days ago. I now fried onions
in an eino ben yomo fleishik pot
and I want to put them into
whatever I'm going to use them with.
Okay, I have some of those onions
left over. You cannot eat those onions
with milchik. Okay, they don't make you
milchik. That's a very important caveat. That
does not make you milchik, but they
should not be eaten with dairy. What
if b'diavad these fried onions, do fried
onions carry the same status as raw
onions? That's my question. Wait, what do
you mean? It's charif either way. Yeah,
yeah. It, it depends. If, if you
maybe cook them they lose their charifus.
That's my question. They could lose charifus,
but once you start with them in
the pot it's already done. I'm saying
b'diavad. No, somebody fried the onion in
an eino ben yomo fleishik pot. I
told you before I'm going to say
I'm gonna hang up, it doesn't matter.
No, no, you take them and then
you transfer them to a milchik eino
ben yomo pot. B'diavad, is the food
okay? B'diavad, not l'chat-chila. The moment you
put an onion in that pot, fried
or raw? That's my question. Either way.
Once it starts, and you don't, it
doesn't start as a fried onion. So
it starts as a raw onion. It
doesn't matter, once it's cut. There are
situations we talked about in the last
zman of things losing their charifus, but
it doesn't really happen that often. Meaning
we assume that once that onion's in
the pot it's considered davar charif with
everything else. Right. Yeah. What if you,
if you fried a, an onion in
a parve pot, then put it in
a fleishik pot? Yeah, that doesn't matter.
Yeah, but then you put it in
a fleishik pot. No, no, wait. If
I cut an onion with a parve
knife in a parve pot, let's, let's
take a step back. Onions, onions are,
onions are parve. Onions are not meat.
He's got a point. And we're getting
off, we're getting off topic. Yeah, quickly,
quickly. Okay, parve pot, parve knife, parve
board, parve onion, everything's parve. You cut
it up, you, you sauté it. At
that point it loses its charifus, it's
done. And then you put it in
a fleishik pot and then you eat
it with dairy. That's also, doesn't matter.
That's fine, that doesn't have charifus anymore.
Okay, that's what we were looking for.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, weiter. Okay, a
very, very interesting shayla now. So if
you, if you look in the Pischei
Teshuva, if you look in the Pischei
Teshuva in Sif Kattan Aleph. Okay. Tzadi
hey, Pischei Teshuva at the bottom, Sif
Kattan Aleph, he's going to quote a
Pri Megadim, a Minchas Yaakov, which is
the Pri Megadim. Okay. What is the,
the halacha we're going to discuss? Tzadi
hey, Sif Kattan Aleph, tzadi hey. Which
siman? Tzadi hey. Pischei Teshuva is on
the second page at the bottom. Right
there. That's Sif Kattan Aleph. Pischei Teshuva.
What? what? Seif katan aleph? Aleph. Aleph.
Aleph. Doesn't come. Okay. The following shaila
was asked. If I have a pot,
I have a pan. In that pan
I have cheese, maybe they're not even
touching each other, maybe they are. I
have cheese and I have food, okay?
Whatever that is, a potato, broccoli, doesn't
matter whatever it is, okay? It's all
happening in a pareve pot, okay? They're
all, everything's happening together. So there's a
few shailos here. Number one, does this
pan become milchig? Okay. Also what would
we consider about the food? Okay? Do
we assume they're not cooked together? I'm
not throwing it all into a big
pot of boiling water where everything is
mixed around. I have on one side
I have cheese and on one side
I have a potato. Okay? So, if
you look in the Pischei Teshuva he's
going to quote this, this is a,
this is a big big, wait hold
on one second, this is a big
big machlokes here, okay? So they're all,
they're in the same, they're being fried
in the same pan and then I
take that broccoli, okay? Or that potato
and I put it in a pareve
pan. So the shaila is what what
is the status of the non-cheese item
and does it affect the now pareve
pan? Okay? We good? Good. Says the
Pischei Teshuva, עיין שם ה\"ד פרי מגדים.
He quotes the Pree Megadim, the Mishbetzos
Zahav seif katan alef, שכתב בשם שערי
דורא דאין נט בר נט אלא בכלי.
The only time I really talk about
nat bar nat to be meikil on
something is if it happens through a
kli. Aval lo be'ochel. But not if
it's actually talking about food items, okay?
Not if it's actually talking about food
items. Why would that be? So he
can be more, he's ma'arich a lot
here in this Pischei Teshuva. We'll come
back to a little bit later in
the Chavos Daas in the end of
this later down the road, okay? That's
opinion number one. So if I took
that broccoli out of the pot or
that potato and I put it in
a pareve pan, what is that potato?
Milchig. That is straight up milchig according
to the Pree Megadim, okay? There's no
nat bar nat because it was together
with food. Was it cooked? They're cooking
together. Oh, they're cooking together. They're cooking
together. There's another opinion, it's not here
in the notes. There's another opinion of
the Pnei Aryeh that paskens that, I'm
sorry you can see it right here,
עיין תשובות פני אריה סימן טו שהאריך
להוכיח דנוסחא זה בשערי דורא שבפרי מגדים,
he goes to the next level, ואמת
הדין דבאוכל נמי אמרינן נט בר נט.
No, says the Pnei Aryeh, no, there's
nat bar nat is the same thing.
So therefore if I made cheese and
broccoli together, I took out the broccoli
and then I cooked that broccoli with
a I don't know, a potato, what's
that potato? It's a nat bar nat
potato. Follow that? According to the Pree
Megadim, if I take the broccoli, I
really need items here, if I take
the broccoli out and I put it
into another pot and I cook pareve
in that pot, I made whatever's in
that pot dairy, okay? So because the
broccoli is dairy, I don't care that
it wasn't actually cooked with cheese, it
was cooked next to cheese, okay? Shomer
negiah. Is that like saying chanan? Hold
on hold on not really because you
wouldn't need shishim kenegedo. Hold on hold
on hold on hold on what hold
on hold on. Then you have the
Pnei Aryeh. The Pnei Aryeh says no,
nat bar nat. I have broccoli, it
didn't get cooked with cheese, so maybe
it was in netinas taam? Yes, yes.
Could you eat that broccoli with meat?
Absolutely not. I took that broccoli, I
put it into a pareve pan with
a potato, could I eat that potato
according to the Shulchan Aruch lechatchila with
cheese? Yes. According to the Rama lechatchila
no, bedieved yes. Got it? With meat.
Whatever. You know what I meant. The
other way, okay? Now, now if you
go to the back, you don't have
to do this, so not going to,
in the back of the Shulchan Aruch
is the Chavos Daas, Rav Yaakov Milisa
and in the Chavos Daas in the
back in tzadi hey, just if you
want to learn this a little bit
later, in tzadi hey, okay so if
you look in the Chavos Daas there's
two things, there's Biurim, so hold on,
there's Biurim and then there's Chiddushim. Biurim
is his explanation of the Shulchan Aruch,
Chiddushim are more more things that are
you know chiddushim. So in tzadi hey,
which should be if you have the
red one on page kaf, if you
don't find it, great, we're not spending
So, sif katan beis, it's not that
long, but here in sif katan beis,
he quotes like a third opinion, the
Chavas Daas, who takes like a little
bit of an in-between approach between the
Pri Megadim and the Pnei Aryeh. What?
In the biurim? I'm sorry, in the
chidushim, in beis. So it's not that
big. So he says not bar not
דוקא כשנטעם אחד בכלי וטעם אחד באוכל.
He says that not bar not applies
as long as one of the transfers
happened through a kli. So if I
have cheese and broccoli in the same
pan, then like it would be not
bar not, but you know, it's a
little bit of a hybrid opinion. Okay.
In the end of the day, halacha
l'maiseh, how do we posken? So look
in the Aruch HaShulchan. Okay, if you
look in the Aruch HaShulchan in source
thirteen. So the Aruch HaShulchan says the
following. Yeah, the Aruch HaShulchan says, let
me just pull it up here. Okay,
says Aruch HaShulchan ודע דגם נט בר
נט דהיתרא לא אמרינן רק כשנטעם הראשון
היה בכלי like the Pri Megadim והשני
במאכל כמו בדגים שעלו בקערה שכתבנו. אבל
כשגם טעם הראשון היה במאכל, but if
the actual ta'am was not through a
pot, but actual piece of food, לא
שרינן נט בר נט. Okay. That is
how the Aruch HaShulchan poskens, just like
the Pri Megadim, that don't even bring
up not bar not if they're in
the pan together, because that ta'am is
a strong transfer, it is not just
nesinas ta'am, it's real ta'am, and therefore
it doesn't work. Now if you go
to the Yad Yehuda in source fourteen,
he poskens like the Chavas Daas. Bigdeira
shel basar, he says the following. ודוקא
בבלוע אחד בקדירה והשני באוכל, right? Just
like we said, like the Chavas Daas.
As long as one of the flavors
was through the kli, you can consider
it not bar not. ולאו דוקא מתחילה
כלי ואחר כך, doesn't matter, as long
as there was a pot involved somewhere
along the way. או עדי מתחילה אוכל
ואחר כך כלי. Okay. Now go to
the other line. Says a very important
caveat. מיהו אם נתבשלו הדגים בחלב ממש.
I'm talking about where you had one
pan. Like you live in Jools and
he's got that one pan. So what
do they do? They make a little
mechitzah in the pan, a little bit
of broccoli on one side, a little
bit of cheese on the other side.
But if you mamash cooked the dagim
becholov mamash with real milk, אין נחשב
זה לבלוע כיון דגוף החלב נכנס בהם.
That's not considered nesinas ta'am. You know
what that broccoli is? Milchig. וכן רוטב
של בשר לא נחשב לטעם, if I
have gravy, רק נחשב לבעין של בשר.
So says the Yad Yehuda, we're only
lenient when they merely touch each other
without liquid. But if they're like swimming
around together, that's not, don't even discuss
not bar not, that's an issue. You
have cholov, you have everything, it doesn't
even begin. And that's Rav Ovadia in
the next source, in source sixteen. So
Rav Ovadia poskens the following. Rav Ovadia
poskens that not bar not applies even
with two foods. Says Rav Ovadia נותן
טעם בר נותן טעם דהיתרא shekasavnu l'hatir
l'chatchila. Sefardim posken l'chatchila. לא רק אם
היה הטעם ראשון בכלי וטעם שני באוכל
שנתבשל בו. אפילו אם היה הטעם ראשון
באוכל, even if the first thing is
a food, like we're just discussing. ומן
האוכל נפלט טעם באוכל אחר, everything is
considered not bar not. It is not
true that all Sefardi poskim follow Rav
Ovadia, they do not all follow Rav
Ovadia, but Rav Ovadia, who one of
the greatest things Rav Ovadia did was
to bring back Maran Beis Yosef, that
this is what the Shulchan Aruch poskens.
So Rav Ovadia says, broccoli and cheese,
that is not bar not. I take
that broccoli out, I put it in
a parve pan, I could eat that
with straight-up fleishig. Okay, that's Rav Ovadia.
We are machmir a little bit more
like the Pri Megadim and like the
Aruch HaShulchan. You're saying that's from the
original same pot on each different side
of the pan? Yes. Okay. Okay. So,
if you go back, okay, if you
go back, hold on a second. Yeah,
now go back to that original Pis'chei
Teshuva. Okay. What happens, and this is
an interesting shaila because this actually does
happen. I am cooking something in a
pot, I'm cooking my regular vegetables in
a pot, well it's whatever the pot
is, the parve pot, and then on
the outside, something hits the pot, something
splatters onto the pot. We discussed in
the last zman about bitul and things
like that in the pot, things like
that. The shaila is, I don't have...
So we're not even going to discuss
it. The question is, is that nesinas
tam an issue? Because is that nesinas
tam an issue? So if you look
on the, if you go to that
Piskei Teshuva and you go to the
next page which if you have the
red Shulchan Aruch says Kuf Pe Alef
and the top line he quotes the
Chavas Daas. Okay. So again, do I
say that the milk flavor went from
the milk to the pot and then
from the pot to the to the
potatoes? Which would mean that according to
the Shulchan Aruch, doesn't matter. According to
the Rema, if I was if I
have a parve I did everything right.
I listened and I took a parve
pot and I made the potatoes and
it's great and I'm going to have
those parve potatoes, maybe I'm going to
make them with fleishig, okay? I'm going
to make a, whatever, potatoes and meat.
And then I take milk and I'm
also not being so careful and milk
splatters all over the side of the
pot. So now do I say that
and there's no shishim? The milk hit
the pot, the pot hit the potatoes.
According to the Shulchan Aruch, you're great.
Go ahead. According to the Rema, you
can't do anything anymore. You can't have
them with fleishig anymore. B'di'eved if I
forgot, then it would be okay, right?
So that's a shaila. So he quotes
the Chavas Daas. Okay, or sorry, the
other way to say it is that
that's ridiculous, Rabbi. Why would you say
something like that? Nat bar nat applies
when like there's an actual like cooking
process, not just like it hit the
wall of the pot. Im Chavas Daas
שכתב עוד דלא אמרינן נט בר נט
בשעת בישול כגון שנפל חלב על הקדירה
שמבשלים דגים נגד הרוטב that the nat
bar nat does not apply while cooking,
right? If in this situation those potatoes,
they're they're going to be considered dairy.
If that pot is hot and the
thing is cooking, I do not say
nat bar nat. Nat bar nat, remember,
is always a kula. Generally a kula,
you say those words, it's because we're
being lenient. I have a pot of
potatoes, it's cooking, milk hits it, that
is what? Those are dairy potatoes. Don't
even discuss nat bar nat, says the
Chavas Daas. ואחר כך בישלו דגים עם
בשר אפילו בדיעבד אסור אם לא היה
ששים בבשר נגד החלב שנפל בראשונה. Okay.
So says the Chavas Daas, we would
not say nat bar nat in this
situation. You could, you couldn't add because
אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה. Well what's the
issur? No, could you would be mevatel
what's now considered dairy. According to the
Rema, the issur would be that you
can't, you can't eat it l'chat'chila. Yeah,
okay. Now if you skip down a
few lines to the last few lines,
he quotes the Beis Ephraim. The Beis
Ephraim says no, but he quotes the
Teshuvos Beis Ephraim, חלק יורה דעה סימן
לז be'emtza hateshuva. That's a great, that's
like a huge in the vernacular, that's
a huge flex. Like I'm not going
to tell you where this is, it's
in the middle of the teshuva so
you don't have to go like start
searching for it. Okay, good that you
should know. She'hisig alav, and he argues
on the Chavas Daas, והעלה דאפילו בשעת
בישול אמרינן נט בר נט. No, the
Beis Ephraim says that that would still
be considered nat bar nat. So if
you look in the packet in source
16 in the Minchas Chein. So how
do we pasken halacha l'maaseh? So we
Ashkenazim, don't worry. What are we going
to be? Machmir. Okay. If anything of
smichas chaver I showed you is that
we are always machmir. וטעם סבירא ליה
דלכתחילה יש להחמיר בזה, says the Minchas
Chein, we should be machmir, שהמאכל שבתוך
הקדירה בזמן שנפל עליה טיפת בשר the
food that's in my pot בזמן שנפל
עליה טיפת בשר, אי לית בקידרה ששים
כנגד if I don't have shishim shelo
yochelnu b'chalav, כפי שכתב יד יהודה, we
should be machmir, we should be machmir
to hold like this. דהא על כל
פנים מדי ספק לא נפקא ויש להחמיר
מספק כחוות דעת. So v'chen Kaf HaChaim,
דכיון דיש פלוגתא הכא לכתחילה אין לבשל
עם הבשר. So we're machmir that if
this would happen, I didn't have shishim
in my pot, I'd be machmir against
it. Kegon if the pot is hot.
Correct. Correct, because it's cooking. Otherwise, otherwise
known as no nesinas tam at all,
right? You just wash it off. אם
נפל חלב בשעת בישול, okay, if milk
falls while I'm cooking, מבחוץ נגד הרוטב
על הקדירה שמבשלים בה פרוה and I'm
making parve inside this pot. V'lo haya
so again, I'm making potatoes, some milk
falls onto those potatoes the pot, there
is not in the pot shishim against
the milk, right? We're good, I've said
that right? Yeah. Great job. לא יבשל
הפרווה עם בשר says the Minchas Kohein,
you should not cook that parve food
with meat because it's not a situation
of nat bar nat. It's it's dairy.
Very good. U'bediavad, im bishal kvar v'yeish
hefsed meruba, יש לסמוך על המתירים. Okay,
you want to rely on the Kaf
Hachayim with others in case of hefsed
meruba, one would be allowed. And this
is if you look in source 17,
the Sefardi Poskim. Guess what? Sefardi Poskim,
they don't hold like the Chavos Da'as,
they hold like the Beis Ephraim. Says
Rav Ovadia, וגם דין נט בר נט
afilu b'sha'as bishal, טיפת חלב שנפל על
הקדירה שמבשלים בה ירקות. I'm cooking vegetables
and a little bit of milk falls
in, מותר לבשל הירקות אחר מיכן בכלי
אחר עם בשר. Eh, you're fine. But
even according to Ashkenazim, what's the nafkamina?
No, you're not milchig. You're not milchig.
If it falls in, what's the reason
you're fine? Is there shishim or? No
shishim. What's the reason what? What's the
reason that you're fine if it falls
in? It's nat bar nat! Because it's
nat bar nat because even if it
falls right on... No, no, no, on
the outside! On the outside, we're talking
about the outside. Outside, outside. If it
falls inside, you need shishim. Otherwise it's
clear what you're saying. There is... we
learned last night that we're going to
talk about in a second about giving
it to the goy to taste, but...
You need shishim there or? No shishim,
no shishim. If you had shishim everybody's
fine. If you had shishim everybody's fine.
It's very... it's sometimes very hard to
know how to measure shishim, but if
you had shishim you'd be fine. But
the clear point is for Ashkenazim if
it falls on the outside of the
pot, you can't have it, and Sefardim
say... Oi, no one says you can't
have it. Everybody says you can eat
it. No, no, but l'chatchila... with the
opposite thing. B'diavad is l'chatchila. Correct. Correct.
Okay, very good. Vaiter. And the pot
becomes milchig, right? If the status changed,
the pot's status also changed. No, no.
The pot's not milchig. Why is that?
That was on the bechinah. Yeah. The
food inside, what... you don't have to...
the... yeah. Yeah. Okay. Okay. So what...
one more piece that's very important. If
you look in source 18, and we
have to remember this. We've been talking
about nat bar nat because I have
a muttar thing and milk, I have,
you know, and then I have multiple
muttar items. Okay? So the question is
how much are they nesinas ta'am. But,
says the Aruch Hashulchan in source number
18. If the initial flavor that was
cooked in that pot is treifus. So,
when I have nat bar nat, it's
because I cooked macaroni and cheese this
morning. Macaroni and cheese, assuming you made
it kosher, is kosher. Then I clean
out the pot and I make meatballs.
Meatballs, also kosher. I have two kosher
items. The question is how much nesinas
ta'am was there? Okay. If I woke
up that morning and said today's just
not a kosher day, and I made
treifus in the pot, I don't care
about nat bar nat, nat bar nat,
nat bar nat, nat bar nat. It
doesn't matter. Why? Because it's treif. Says
the Aruch Hashulchan, וזה יסוד דין נט
בר נט. The Aruch Hashulchan explains that
again, if I took non-kosher meat and
I cooked non-kosher meat in a pot,
then I later clean that pot and
new water is heated within 24 hours,
that water is... I know this is
going to sound confusing... that water is
not nat bar nat. Okay? So within
24 hours, ah, what about nesinas ta'am?
No, no, no, there is no... we
don't care. You... it's treif. Treif is
treif. After 24 hours, there's maybe what
to discuss. The Aruch Hashulchan says the
following: וזה יסוד דין נט בר נט.
This is one of the most yesod-dik
things, foundational ideas of nat bar nat.
הכלי כהאי גוונא שהמאכל בלע מכלי בשר
בן יומו that the food that had
absorbed fleishig from earlier that day מותר
לאכול המאכל הזה עם חלב and I
cooked something later and I could eat
it with milchig. Mishum de-niklash ha-ta'am. The
whole point here is that the ta'am
is weakened. והוי נט בר נט. So
I made meatballs this morning. When I
made macaroni and cheese later today, yes,
it's not ideal, but the ta'am is
so weakened that there's there's what to
discuss that if I'm sorry if I
made parve in there, not milchig. If
I made noodles in there, that... okay,
so nat bar nat. ואין דין רק
בשר עם חלב וחלב עם בשר. De-keivan
de-ta'am sheini, the second ta'am, whatever I
do later, אקדי של היתר ואיתכחש כולי
האי לא חשיב לאיסור and it's been
weakened so it's not... Aval davar issur
כל היכא דאיכא טעמא אוסר עד סוף
העולם. It doesn't, it doesn't ever. Now,
it might, it might dissipate over time,
and that would be a, that would
be a part of it. After 24
hours, that treifus would if you, if
you made meatballs and you dumped milk
in there, and then you had mamish
basar b'chalav, that pot is treifus. So
if I made anything in that pot
of the next 24 hours, that's that's
straight up treifa. Okay? You'd have to
kasher that pot. You don't wait 24
hours and then say, well, you know,
the rabbis don't be like, oh, you
waited 24 hours, you can use it
again. And that would be, that would
be amazing. We don't say that. We
say that for basar, we say that
for for these kind of issues because
the taam is weakened. But if it's
treifus, then you'd have to you'd have
to really, you know, probably kasher. How'd
it have to be kashered if you
did that? If you did what? Cooked
non-kosher. Like you made macaroni and cheese
in the morning, and then in the
afternoon you cleaned it out and then
in the afternoon you made meat, you
might be able to eat some pieces,
but the pot still has to be
kashered. That's treif. We generally tell you
to kasher a pot like that. Yeah,
there's makom l'hakel if if you live
with Jules and you had that one
pot then you'd have to, you know,
I have three pots. It's been a
good year. Yeah. Okay fine. What? Okay.
So here's a very practical example. Source
19. Source 19. Okay? What happens, a
person wants to heat up a baby
bottle, okay, of milk in a parve
pot. Okay? So looking Sefer Megillas Sefer
the following: חמם לתינוק בקבוק חלב בתוך
מים חמים בכלי פרוה. I took a
parve pot, I heated it up with
hot water, and I put a milchig
bottle in there. So the shaileh is
דין זה תלוי במחלוקת חוות דעת ובית
אפרים שהביא הפתחי תשובה בראש סימן צ''ה
we just saw it. דלפי הבית אפרים
אין המים שבכלי מקבלים את טעם החלב
באופן ישיר אלא רק דרך דופן הבקבוק.
The taam hachalev, is it bar nat
bar? והגיע טעם החלב לכלי יש כאן
ג' נותן טעם ומותר לכולי עלמא. אבל
לפי החוות דעת נחשב החלב כאילו נפל
ישירות לתוך המים. So according to the
Chavos Daas it's an issue. We follow
this psak. We follow this psak. Person
heats up a bottle of milk, they
shouldn't heat it up in a milchig
pot because you heat it up in
a, you know, besides besides the Shabbos
issues of hatmana you have to be
careful about that also, but if you
heat it up in a parve pot
it's going to make a it's going
to create milchig status-ish of. But I
feel like just pointed out, you don't
warm a bottle to yad soledes bo,
you don't warm a bottle that much
because it's for a baby. What's the
matter? What's the matter? I have boiling
hot water. I put a milchig bottle
in there. It's in boiling hot water.
Sure you did. I've done that! It
all turned out okay. I don't I
don't give the baby the cup of
hot water. We're not the 1950s anymore.
I don't give yes. You don't give
the baby boiling hot milk. Yeah, then
they hold the cup with the pinky
up. No. They okay, fine. Vaiter, moving
on. Okay. One more very interesting thing
they point out here. I'm going to
skip a whole thing about the Sous
Vide. If you're interested you can read
it in the notes. What? Why? Because
it's not mareh mekomos on it, it's
just me reading what they have to
say. So I could read it for
you, but it's a big machlokes about
how poskim view the Sous Vide because
can you use the same Sous Vide
for milchigs and fleishigs? But could you
heat up if a person puts, okay,
challah... what's a Sous Vide? So a
Sous Vide is a you take a
piece of meat or chicken, it doesn't
matter which one, and you it's like
vacuum sealed in a plastic-ish wrapper, okay,
and you it's you put some you
can put spice in it or whatever,
but it sits in there in this
container and then it basically cooks it
till like it's most perfect temperature. Whatever.
You got there's a video here, you
can watch it, you can have a
great time. You can have a great
time. I'm going to move on. What's
the machlokes? Can you use it for
both? And the answer is it's a
machlokes. Yeah. The maiseh Sefardim say you
could use Sefardim say you could use
a Sous Vide in a parve pot
for cooking dairy and the other way
around. We're a little bit more Ashkenazim
are more Ashkenazim are more machmir. Ashkenazim
really you know, you'll watch the video.
You'll watch the video. It's going to
it's going to take too long. Do
you reuse the bags? Why would you?
Right. It's right. That's a good explanation.
You have one or no? Yeah. It's
a water bath. Right. Right. Yeah, very
interesting by the way. There's another shaileh
very also comes up. People they heat
up challah... that you could potentially use
a challah from Shabbos for French toast
on Sunday, assuming that you just cut
it and it was a big loaf
and you took it off the table.
But if you heated up that challah
on top of a crockpot, that's fleishig.
Not going to make it fleishig but
you cannot use that. What? If, however,
if, if, if you wrap it with
something underneath, then we're more meikel on
that. Because of... what? It's still in
the bag. Yeah, I don't know. Because
when you only have one pot, you
don't have... All right, weiter. All right,
we got to learn Torah. Moving on.
Okay. Go to the Gemara in Pesachim,
source 20. Okay. We're now going to
get into the issue of mixing fish
and meat together. Okay. Okay. Says the
Gemara in Pesachim. Hahu binita, there's this
kind of fish de'ituvei bahadi bisra that
they would make it with some kind
of meat. So assera Rava miparzikiya. So
this Rava would look... would asser lemichlei
bechuscha. He would say you could not
eat this this fish with milchig. Okay?
מר בר רב אשי אמר אפילו במילחא
נמי אסורא. Oh, says the Gemara. Right,
the Gemara says, well there's actually a
Gemara earlier in Ayin Vav that they
also didn't quote. The Gemara talks about
reicha, okay? Gemara talks about reicha. That,
you know, baking things on separate trays
but in the same oven is an
issue of reicha. We pasken l'chatchila reicha's
an issue, right? That if I if
I had a baking sheet of, you
know, I don't know, if I have
a tray of chicken in my oven
and a tray of pareve cookies in
my oven, so you're not fleishig if
you ate those cookies, but but you
shouldn't eat them with milchig because of
reicha. Because of reicha. Fine. The Gemara
here in Pesachim in source 20, the
Gemara is discussing the next thing and
that is within the opinion that says
reicha is something, we call reicha miltza,
reicha lav miltza. Is reicha an actual
entity or not? So the Gemara here
discusses eating fish and meat baked in
the same oven. So the Gemara says
that if I made this fish in
the same oven as the meat, bahadi
bisra, Rava says you cannot eat that
fish with milchig, okay? And Rav Ashi
comes in and says and this is
what the Gemara ends with, אפילו במילחא
נמי אסורא. Not only that but even
to eat it with salt is asur
משום דקשי לריחא ולדבר אחר. So if
you look at this fascinating Rashi on
the left side, Rashi says, so now
I can't eat it baked in the
same oven because of the mixture of
meat and fish causes bad breath, קשי
לריחא ולדבר אחר. And what does it
cause me? Tzara'as. So says the Gemara,
do not eat this. Not only Rava
has one reason, you can't eat it
with milchig, and he says even to
eat it with salt is a problem
because it's going to cause an issue.
The Mordechai in the bottom here in
source 21. And Mordechai says the following
conclusion. The Mordechai says, well, the Gemara
paskens that ונראה לי אהא דמכאן נזהרים
באשכנז וצריכים לאכול דג ובשר זה אחר
זה בלא קינוח. This is where what...
I can't eat fish and meat... that
fish, I'm sorry, that was cooked with
meat nor could I eat fish and
meat together, okay? Without doing what? Kinu'ach.
ומיהו משמע דאין סכנה כי אם דרך
בישול ולהאכל יחד. That really it seems
to be asur is asur to eat
them together but it seems that you
would be allowed to eat fish and
then meat because those are separate. What
do we seem to asser here? Eating
them together. Keep going to source 22.
Says the Tur at the top. Wait
one second one second one second. Says
the Tur at the top. How do
we pasken? So the Tur says, eating
fish and meat together is a problem
וצריך להיזהר שלא לאכול בשר ודג ביחד.
We do not eat fish and meat
together she'kasha l'tzara'as. It causes tzara'as v'yesh
machmirim badavar. And there are those that
are even more machmir ואפילו דגים כלים
לבדם. Not only do they not eat
them together, they even have separate keilim.
And then he quotes he quotes v'adoni
avi haRosh. He quotes the Ro... his
father the Rosh. הוא רגיל לרחוץ ידיו
בין בשר לדג. He would be machmir
to wash his hands between meat and
fish. היה שורה פת ביין. Back to
this issue that it's always better to
just wash and have bread. ואוכל בינתיים
כדי לרחוץ פיו. That his father argued
on the Mordechai. And it says no,
the Mordechai, by the way, and the
Rosh and the Mordechai were chavrusas. The
Rosh and the Mordechai were chavrusas until
the Mordechai is killed in the Rindfleisch
massacres, and which is what motivates the
Rosh to leave Germany. So the Mordechai
says, it's mashma from the Gemara that
I can't cook them together, I can't
eat them together, but I'll eat meat
and I'll eat fish and I don't
have to wash anything, because the says
the Rosh, no, it is not only
assur to eat them together, it is
assur even to eat them one after
the other without any kind of washing.
Yeah, you can eat one and then
wash your hands and mouth and everything,
that is how the Rosh paskens. So
if you look here in the next
source, in source 23, this is how
we pasken halacha lemaise. We pasken halacha
lemaise, which we'll just go through this
pretty quickly. צריך להיזהר שלא לאכול בשר
ודג ביחד שקשה לצרעת, exactly like we
just saw, וכן אין לצלות בשר עם
דג משום ריח, you can't roast them
at the same time. Bedieved eino assur.
Gimmel: ירחץ ידיו בין בשר לדג ויאכל
פת שביניהם לרחוץ פיו. Daled: ויש אומרים
אין לחוש בזה, like that's the Mordechai,
אלא רק שבשלם יחד ואכלן אבל לאכלן
זה אחר זה אין לחוש, that's the
Mordechai, maybe you don't have to. Vechein
nohagin, and says the Shulchan Aruch, this
is how we pasken, לא לרחוץ הפה
ולא הידיים ביניהם. We don't do anything,
we don't eat them together, we don't
cook them together, but you can eat
one after the other. ומכל מקום יש
לאכול דבר ביניהם ולשתות דהוי קינוח והדחה.
You should do something. I don't say
you have to go full on wash
your hands, mouth, and feet, but you
should eat something and wash your mouth
out a little bit so that you
don't have some of these concerns. So
what we're going to talk about next
time is about all these issues, fish
bittel issues, you know, we're going to
try to pronounce Worcestershire sauce a number
of times.